"Mercury Exposure from Tuna vs. Thimerosal in Vaccines"
Once upon a time,
routine childhood vaccinations
used a preservative
containing mercury
called thimerosal.
I was always surprised
by parents
who didn't want
to vaccinate their kids
for fear of exposing them
to mercury,
yet went on to feed them tuna.
Each thimerosal-containing shot
would inject roughly
the same amount of mercury
that's in a can of tuna fish.
And while a child
may only get a half dozen
or so mercury-containing shots,
they could be eating
tuna salad sandwiches
year after year.
So, it's evident
that kids would be exposed
to less mercury from vaccines
than they would
if they ate fish.
Though when the mercury
is injected,
the absorption
is like 100%,
whereas if we just eat it,
some passes right through.
We used to think
the gastrointestinal absorption
of mercury was close to 100%.
Following ingestion
of the mercury in fish,
the more updated estimates
are consistently less than 100%.
On the other hand,
the form of mercury in fish
is worse than the form
of mercury used in vaccines,
which is excreted from the body
much more quickly.
The mercury in fish represents
the greater threat to children,
but because any potential risk
is a concern,
in 1999,
the Public Health Service,
the American Academy
of Pediatrics,
and vaccine manufacturers,
agreed that
thimerosal-containing vaccines
should be removed
as quickly as possible.
And by 2001,
thimerosal was removed
from all vaccines
in the recommended
childhood immunization schedule.
Currently, in the United States,
only multidose vial flu vaccines
contain thimerosal,
and thimerosal-free flu shots
are widely available.
Flumist,
the nasal spray vaccine,
is mercury-free,
as well as most
of the single-dose vials
used for pregnant women,
which anyone can request.
Of course, Thimerosal
is still used
in infants' vaccines
in developing countries.
If the mercury load
is deemed unacceptable
in North America and Europe,
why should it
be given to infants
in other parts of the world?
We could also ask,
if we want to play it safe
and not expose kids
to that much mercury,
should we be feeding them fish,
since kids are constantly
getting that much mercury
in their meals,
and it's methylmercury,
which is even worse
than the mercury in vaccines.
Now, there are ways
to mitigate the mercury
if you can't beat
some tuna craving.
Drinking green tea with a meal
may help block
some of the absorption
of mercury when eating fish.
Normally, the recommendation
is to not drink tea with meals,
because it can also block
the absorption of iron,
but that's better
than the other way
to protect yourself,
shooting up with heroine.
For some reason, the activation
of opioid receptors
protects nerves
from mercury toxicity.